<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
      <fileDesc xml:id="STqrst">
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Marcellus Franckheim to s.n.. 1618-07-01</title>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>
                  <surname>Petrolini</surname>
                  <forename>Chiara</forename>
               </persName>
               <resp>Data acquisition</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>
                  <surname>Wallnig</surname>
                  <forename>Thomas</forename>
               </persName>
               <resp>Data curation</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>The Tengnagel Correspondence Data</edition>
            <principal>
               <forename>Thomas</forename>
               <surname>Wallnig</surname>
            </principal>
            <funder ref="https://www.fwf.ac.at/forschungsradar/10.55776/P30511">FWF P 30511</funder>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName>Phaidra</orgName>
               <ref target="https://phaidra.univie.ac.at/">https://phaidra.univie.ac.at/</ref>
            </publisher>
            <date type="first" when="2024">2024</date>
            <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>
            <availability status="free">
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-Sharealike 4.0 International (CC BY-SA 4.0)</licence>
            </availability>
            <idno>STS0103</idno>
            <idno type="URI">http://XYZ</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <noteGrp type="mentions">
               <note>
                  <listBibl/>
               </note>
               <note>
                  <listPlace>
                     <place ref="ST_Place_0011">
                        <placeName>Hungary</placeName>
                     </place>
                     <place ref="ST_Place_0109">
                        <placeName>Austria</placeName>
                     </place>
                  </listPlace>
               </note>
               <note>
                  <listPerson>
                     <person ref="ST_Pers_0097">
                        <persName>Ferdinand II</persName>
                     </person>
                  </listPerson>
               </note>
            </noteGrp>
            <noteGrp type="editorial"/>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc type="composite">
               <msIdentifier facs="http://data.onb.ac.at/rep/10028395">
                  <institution>Austrian National Library</institution>
                  <repository>Department of Manuscripts and Rare Books</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">Cod. 9737s</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <biblScope unit="page">152r–153v</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="Tengnagel">letter</classCode>
         </textClass>
         <correspDesc ref="STS0103">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName xml:id="ST_Pers_0623">Marcellus Franckheim</persName>
               <placeName xml:id="ST_Place_0097">Bratislava</placeName>
               <date when="1618-07-01">1 July 1618</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName xml:id="">s.n.</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language>latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <cell style="font-size: 11pt;">This is not a letter, but a poem about Ferdinand's incoronation. 

Si apre con dei versi sulla Madonna, patrona della corona d'Ungheria, per poi celebrare Ferdinando come restauratore della pace e come un sole dell'austria. Questo carme non fu mai pubblicato. Perché finisce tra le carte di ST? Non lo sappiamo. Sappiamo però che Marcellus subito dopo l'incoronazione avrebbe perso il suo posto di segretario del cardinal Khesl (che fu incarcerato subito dopo in un Tirolo, per poi a&lt;ndare a roma e tornare a Vienna solo dopo molti anni) e invece restò in buoni rapporti con la corte, tanto da accompagnare in viaggio Don Matthias, figlio di Rodolfo II. 
Le successive lettere di Marcellus sono per Francis Gasneb Tengnagel, non per ST, e poi una invece per ST. Perché sono finite qua? 

a prop. di MF: Marcellus Franckheim grew up in Zutphen and received a proper Calvinistic upbringing and education, that eventually led to his function as rector of the Latin school. Despite his Calvinistic background, he remained searching in religious terms and had little personal affinity with extremists. The turning point in his life was his conversion to Catholicism, which also meant the loss of his position as rector. Marcellus exchanged his old Calvinist contacts with a new catholic network that provided him with the opportunity to leave Zutphen and to enter the service of the Habsburg emperor in Vienna. Between 1616 and 1618, Marcellus was secretary to Cardinal Khlesl, the head of emperor Matthias’ Privy Council. In this function Marcellus witnessed the coronations of Matthias’ successor Ferdinand II as king of Bohemia (1617) and Hungary (1618). A year later he would be travelling Europe with Don Matthias of Austria, a bastard son of former emperor Rudolf II, promoting the Ordo Militiae Christianae among the European Catholic nobility and signing his letters with ‘Marcellus Franckheim, Aulae Lateranensis &amp; Sacri Palatii Apostolici Comes, auratus militia Eques (Order of the Golden Spur), a distinction for special achievements for the Catholic church awarded to him by Pope Paul V. Marcellus became a public advocate for the catholic and Habsburg interests, as became apparent from his publication in which he defended Habsburg intervention in Bohemia. Eventually he moved to the Souther Netherlands and became councillor to respectively Archduchess Isabella and King Philip IV of Spain in the Supreme Council of the Admiralty of the Flanders fleet, ministering the actions of Dunkirk privateers in the Spanish-Dutch Eighty Years War.</cell>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
