<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
      <fileDesc xml:id="STqrst">
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Margareta van Wyningen to Sebastian Tengnagel. 1624-11-27</title>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>
                  <surname>Petrolini</surname>
                  <forename>Chiara</forename>
               </persName>
               <resp>Data acquisition</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>
                  <surname>Wallnig</surname>
                  <forename>Thomas</forename>
               </persName>
               <resp>Data curation</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>The Tengnagel Correspondence Data</edition>
            <principal>
               <forename>Thomas</forename>
               <surname>Wallnig</surname>
            </principal>
            <funder ref="https://www.fwf.ac.at/forschungsradar/10.55776/P30511">FWF P 30511</funder>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName>Phaidra</orgName>
               <ref target="https://phaidra.univie.ac.at/">https://phaidra.univie.ac.at/</ref>
            </publisher>
            <date type="first" when="2024">2024</date>
            <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>
            <availability status="free">
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-Sharealike 4.0 International (CC BY-SA 4.0)</licence>
            </availability>
            <idno>STS0211</idno>
            <idno type="URI">http://XYZ</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <noteGrp type="mentions">
               <note>
                  <listPlace>
                     <place ref="ST_Place_0093">
                        <placeName>Hamburg</placeName>
                     </place>
                     <place ref="ST_Place_0113">
                        <placeName>Elbe</placeName>
                     </place>
                  </listPlace>
               </note>
               <note>
                  <listPerson>
                     <person ref="ST_Pers_0480">
                        <persName>Peter Bloem</persName>
                     </person>
                  </listPerson>
               </note>
            </noteGrp>
            <noteGrp type="editorial"/>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc type="composite">
               <msIdentifier facs="http://data.onb.ac.at/rep/10028395">
                  <institution>Austrian National Library</institution>
                  <repository>Department of Manuscripts and Rare Books</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">Cod. 9737s</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <biblScope unit="page">322r–322v</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="Tengnagel">letter</classCode>
         </textClass>
         <correspDesc ref="STS0211">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName xml:id="ST_Pers_0501">Margareta van Wyningen</persName>
               <placeName xml:id="ST_Place_0185">Bruges</placeName>
               <date when="1624-11-27">27 November 1624</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName xml:id="ST_Pers_0070">Sebastian Tengnagel</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language>Dutch</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <cell style="font-size: 11pt;">Widow of Jan van Wyninghen the Elder. Writes Tengnagel because she has received two letters from him, on the 17th and 24th. Writes about her great sadness over losing her husband. Hopes that God will forgive the people who took his life - thus confirming her husband was murdered. Has received a letter from her brother-in-law who writes that one of three people has been arrested in Bleeck (?), who has confessed to being an accomplice in the murder. The other two have fled. Writes she sees Tengnagel as her father, as he has been a good father to her late husband and has always helpen them in their business in advice and deeds. Asks him for advice regarding the Bloem case - she luckily still has his letter even though her husband initially intended to take it along. She had adviced against that and said she would find someone else to take (care of?) it, which was also the reason she did not travel along with her husband. Wishes she would have gone with him. Also wishes she had the money that Bloem owes them. Wants to know what to do before she leaves (to Vienna?) and begs Tengnagel, "dear father", to help her and to take her as his own child. Says she has no one in this country, and says her husband has assured her during his life that Tengnagel would help her if anything happened. Wants help to at least get the money while she has to stay in this country, so that no one else has to come and help her. Does not know how to travel with the dangers and cold, and hopes that one of the brothers-in-law will come with her son to get her as soon as it is possible. Description of her great misery and her prayers to God, being alone in a country where she hoped to find fortune but instead found great misfortune. Puts all her faith and trust in God and in good people around her who can help her. Also asks for advice with regard to her son: should she let him continue his studies to become a doctor of medicine or in law? Wants to travel to Rome with him in the following year, which is a jubilee year, meaning there will be a lot to see and do. Knows that her husband would have gone, but now asks Tengnagel for advice - will do whatever he sees fit. Continues to answer second letter, which she has read and 'washed with her tears'. Writes she was hopeful for a while, but then reeceived a letter on the 23rd from her jongest brother(in-law?) from Hamburg that her husband had been found in the Elbe 7 miles from Hamburg in Artelenborch. Was murdered in the night, three ciriminals have been caught in Bleeck but 2 have escaped. Begs Tengnagel again to take her as his own child and help her and to bring justice. Feels a little embarrassed because she doesn't have much to give in return other than prayers for him and his wife. Says she still have pepper and something else from her husband that has not yet been sold. He had sold a part and had taken all of the profit with him, which became the cause of his death (thus seems to have been killed for his money by robbers). Will try to sell it for the best price possible to get through the winter. Does not want to expose her brother and son, as well as herself, to danger of the travel especially in the winter. Does want to travel to the Netherlands to bury her husband and see him one more time.</cell>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
