<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
      <fileDesc xml:id="STqrst">
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Georg Remus to Sebastian Tengnagel. 1614-06-21</title>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>
                  <surname>Petrolini</surname>
                  <forename>Chiara</forename>
               </persName>
               <resp>Data acquisition</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>
                  <surname>Wallnig</surname>
                  <forename>Thomas</forename>
               </persName>
               <resp>Data curation</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>The Tengnagel Correspondence Data</edition>
            <principal>
               <forename>Thomas</forename>
               <surname>Wallnig</surname>
            </principal>
            <funder ref="https://www.fwf.ac.at/forschungsradar/10.55776/P30511">FWF P 30511</funder>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName>Phaidra</orgName>
               <ref target="https://phaidra.univie.ac.at/">https://phaidra.univie.ac.at/</ref>
            </publisher>
            <date type="first" when="2024">2024</date>
            <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>
            <availability status="free">
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-Sharealike 4.0 International (CC BY-SA 4.0)</licence>
            </availability>
            <idno>STR0196</idno>
            <idno type="URI">http://XYZ</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <noteGrp type="mentions">
               <listBibl type="mentioned">
                  <bibl xml:id="ST_">
                     <title/>
                  </bibl>
               </listBibl>
               <note>
                  <listPlace/>
               </note>
               <note>
                  <listPerson>
                     <person ref="ST_Pers_0260">
                        <persName>Scipione Gentili</persName>
                     </person>
                     <person ref="ST_Pers_0455">
                        <persName>Andreas Dinner</persName>
                     </person>
                     <person ref="ST_Pers_0068">
                        <persName>Konrad Rittershausen</persName>
                     </person>
                     <person ref="ST_Pers_0027">
                        <persName>Marquard Freher</persName>
                     </person>
                     <person ref="ST_Pers_0044">
                        <persName>Mylen</persName>
                     </person>
                     <person ref="ST_Pers_0457">
                        <persName>Schöner</persName>
                     </person>
                     <person ref="ST_Pers_0454">
                        <persName> Johann Wild</persName>
                     </person>
                     <person ref="ST_Pers_0453">
                        <persName>Salomon Schweigger</persName>
                     </person>
                     <person ref="ST_Pers_0456">
                        <persName>Georg Sedel</persName>
                     </person>
                  </listPerson>
               </note>
            </noteGrp>
            <noteGrp type="editorial"/>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc type="composite">
               <msIdentifier facs="http://data.onb.ac.at/rep/10028395">
                  <institution>Austrian National Library</institution>
                  <repository>Department of Manuscripts and Rare Books</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">Cod. 9737r</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>
               <biblScope unit="page">262r–263v</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="Tengnagel">letter</classCode>
         </textClass>
         <correspDesc ref="STR0196">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName xml:id="ST_Pers_0288">Georg Remus</persName>
               <placeName xml:id="ST_Place_0075">Nuremberg</placeName>
               <date when="1614-06-21">21 June 1614</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName xml:id="ST_Pers_0070">Sebastian Tengnagel</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language>Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <cell style="font-size: 11pt;">si nomina Johann Wild (* 1585 as Johann Wild; † after 1619) was a German mercenary from Nuremberg, who fought in the Turkish wars among others at Gran. On December 27 or 28, 1604, he was captured by the Hungarians during the battle of St. Andrä and sold as a slave to the Turks, whose allies were the Hungarians at the time. During his captivity he was one of the first Europeans to visit the Islamic sanctuary of Mecca. Through his experience report the Occident gained detailed knowledge about the Islamic world.The first years after his capture he lived as a slave in Constantinople. He proved to be talented, quickly learned the Turkish language and, after slight difficulties in adapting to Muslim customs, was assigned to administrative tasks. His descriptions suggest a certain education of Wild, because he described local conditions quite accurately with reference to ancient geographers and was able to estimate the value and prices of everyday goods.In 1606 he was sold for the fifth time and brought to Cairo. There he was bought by a Persian merchant. In Cairo he learned the Arabic language. He accompanied the merchant on his business trips, among other things on strenuous caravan journeys to Mecca, Medina, Jeddah, Yemen, Sinai, Jerusalem and Damascus. Since Christians and Jews were forbidden to visit the holy places under penalty of death, it can be assumed that Hans Wild converted to Islam superficially. According to his own statements, he participated in all cultic acts at the grave of the Prophet Mohammed in Medina. Nevertheless, he took advantage of a later stay in Jerusalem to have the patriarch issue him a confirmation of his visit to the tomb of Christ. When its owner found this document, he sold it on in anger. Wild now served an elderly Turk in Cairo, who restored his freedom in 1609. After a first attempt to return failed and his ship was shipwrecked, he returned to Cairo via Cyprus and Antalya. In 1611, Hans Wild returned to his native Nuremberg, where he wrote down his experiences. His report of his experiences was one of the first records in the West of the customs, traditions, landscapes, people and places of Islam in the 17th century. His description of the Islamic sanctuaries refuted some of the rumors that had been spread until then, such as the one about an iron coffin of the Prophet Mohammed, which was held in suspension by a large magnetic stone.

DA RIASSUMERE MEGLIO 

</cell>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
